Julia Collier Harris Papers, 1921-1955
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Julia Collier Harris Papers
1921-1955
Harris, Julia Collier, b. 1875
MS 74
2 boxes (.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Journalist; Civic leader; Editor. Papers consist primarily of correspondence from well known people, including Sherwood Anderson, Louis Bromfield, George Washington Carver, Geraldine Farrar, Dorothy Canfield Fisher, and H. L. Mencken. Also manuscripts, memorabilia, photographs, and newspaper clippings.
Biographical Note
Julia Florida Collier was born to Charles Augustus and Susie Rawson Collier in Atlanta, Georgia in 1875. After finishing Miss Chamberlayne's School in Boston, Harris graduated from Washington Seminary in Atlanta, Georgia where she studied illustration with Henry Sandham. She went on to attend Cowles Art School and the University of Chicago. In 1897 she married Julian LaRose Harris, managing editor of the Atlanta Constitution, and business manager of Uncle Remus's Magazine. In 1913, the Harrises moved to New York, where Julian began work as the Sunday editor of the New York Herald, then as editor and general manager of the Paris Herald. Julia contributed articles and columns to both of these papers. Following Julian's service in World War I, the Harrises became owners of the Columbus Enquirer-Sun in Georgia (1922-29). Julia was associate editor and vice president; wrote articles, editorials and reviewed books; and was a music critic. She also wrote a number of travel and art essays for leading periodicals. Additionally, she was a strong voice in local and national social and civic issues. In 1926, Julia and Julian Harris received the Pulitzer Prize. She also published two biographies of her father-in-law: Life and Letters of Joel Chandler Harris (1918) and Joel Chandler Harris: Editor and Essayist (1931). Julia Collier Harris died in 1967.
[For more biographical information see "Julian and Julia Collier Harris (1874-1963; 1875-1967)" in the New Georgia Encyclopedia: http://www.georgiaencyclopedia.org/nge/Article.jsp?id=h-2459 ]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Julia Collier Harris Papers consist primarily of received correspondence related to the journalistic work of Julia Harris and her husband in support of social and civic improvement, and their work for the Columbus Enquirer- Sun. Among the more than 300 letters are those of Sherwood Anderson, Gamaliel Bradford and George Washington Carver, as well as 137 letters from Geraldine Farrar (after her retirement from Metropolitan Opera to civic and war service). Sixty-seven letters from H.L. Menken and letters from Louis Bromfield, Dorothy Canfield Fisher, Cora Wilson Stewart and numerous other persons of importance are also included. Other materials such as clippings, manuscripts, and photographs are interfiled among some of the correspondence.
This collection also includes typescripts of unpublished papers by Julia Harris for the Atlanta "History Club," Harris' published articles for the Columbus Enquirer-Sun and the Chattanooga Sunday Times, manuscripts of her review of the George Washington Carver biography and impressions of Europe written for the New York Herald Magazine Supplement as well as a memorabilia and a photograph of the Harrises with Sherwood Anderson (1929).
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Julia Collier Harris donated her Papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1955. The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Search Terms
Journalism--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Southern States--Social conditions--20th century--Sources; Women journalists--United States--Biography--Sources; Harris, Julia Collier, b. 1875; Anderson, Sherwood, 1876-1941; Carver, George Washington, 1864?-1943; Farrar, Geraldine, 1882-1967; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956
- Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Anderson, Elizabeth (Mrs. Sherwood) 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anderson, Sherwood (Box 1)
    - Clippings and photographs,n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters to Julian and Julia C. Harris 1925-1936, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Bennet, James O'Donnell 1928 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Boyd, Julian 1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Berndt, Aaron 1924-29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bradford, Gamaliel 1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bradford, Helen F. 1932, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bromfield, Louis 1927, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Brooks, Van Wyck 1933 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Buxton, Frank 1926 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Carver, George Washington (Box 1)
    - "A Brief Sketch of My Life": edited manuscript, booklet and clippings 1929, 1930, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence 1926-39 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Collier, John 1935 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Couch, W.T. 1927 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Dabney, Virginius 1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Farrar, Geraldine (Box 1)
    - Related clippings, programs, and photograph 1944, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Autographed photographn.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence 1925-55 (Box 1, Folder 21-27)
  - Fisher, Dorothy Canfield 1921-27 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Glenn, Isa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Harris, Julia Collier and R. T. Bond 1929 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Harris, Julian La Rose: obituary 1963 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Hubert, Benjamin F 1929 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Huebson, B.W 1925 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Irwin, Inez Haynes 1929, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Johnson, Nunnaly, circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Krutch, Joseph Wood 1925 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Liveright, Horace 1926 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Menken, H.L (Box 1)
    - Descriptive list of his collections, compiled by Betty Adler n.d. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence and clippings 1925-29 (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
  - Morton, Robert R. 1926, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Nock, Albert Jay 1923 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Odum, Howard W. 1925-26 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Peabody, George Foster: correspondence and photographs 1927, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Stewart, Cora Wilson (includes letter from Calvin Coolidge) 1922-27 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Villard, Oswald: invitation to Julian and Julia C. Harris (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - White, William Allen 1927-28 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Miscellaneous letters to Julia C. Harris (Box 2)
    - Business n.d. (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Personal n.d. (Box 2, Folder 49)
- SERIES II: WRITINGS AND MISCELLANEOUS
  - History papers: unpublished typescripts n.d. (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Articles by Julia C. Harris (published)1925-35, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Miscellaneous: photographs, biographical sketches, clippings and memorabilia n.d. (Box 2, Folder 52)